Meeting is starting.
So the recording has started.
I am now letting everybody on in from the
waiting room.
So good morning everybody.
This is Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health and and just
welcoming you all to the Medical
Psilocybin Advisory Board meeting.
The chair is Ian Dunn and the vice chair
is Dan Jennings.
And at this point in time,
I will turn the meeting on over to Dan to
start at things.
But just as a reminder,
we do record this meeting.
And so please make sure to keep language
appropriate for recording as we do put
this out publicly.
And the other thing,
just to remind everyone that is one of
the reasons why we also,
other than board members and some of the
team at DoH, we,
we also keep cameras off for two reasons.
1,
to ensure that there's nothing in the
background that would prohibit us from
posting the video of the meeting onto the
website.
And two,
just in case people are in areas that do
not have great bandwidth.
This way they can actually stay in the
meeting and they don't drop nearly as
often out of the meeting.
And so we do have that and so with that I
will turn the meeting on over to Dan.
So thank you everybody and welcome Dan
meeting is yours appreciate it thank you
very much Dominic and I know that we have
perfect.
We've got an agenda here.
I everybody I'm Dan Jennings,
I'm the chair of the research and
continuous improvement subcommittee and
also the Co chair here of the board.
And so I appreciate everybody being here
today and especially all other board
members that are with us in Department of
Health and all of you from the public
that have decided to to join in for our
regular board meeting.
So I would love if we could go ahead and
call order to make sure that we do have
everybody here.
I know that I see everybody from my board
here.
So I would love it while we're doing this
is to have everybody from the Psilocybin
Advisory Board introduce themselves and
say hi to everybody.
And so we'll start with Brenda.
Good morning, everyone.
Thank you for coming to this meeting
today.
I am Brenda Burgard.
I chair the training and education and
hope this will go really well today and
needing all your participation in,
you know,
forging ahead and making everything great.
OK, Thank you, Sir.
Appreciate it.
And is Alana on Alana dances?
Hi, this is Keenan Ryan.
I am the acting chief medical officer for
Medicaid and I am covering for Doctor
Dances today.
Perfect.
Thank you for being here.
And Desba.
Yeah, it's a good morning, everyone.
I'm Desba, and I chair the Equity,
Access and Cultural Considerations
Committee.
If you have not done so today yet,
take a deep breath and settle in.
This is going to be a great meeting.
Thank you.
That's why I appreciate that.
And Doctor Larry Lehman.
Yeah, Hi, Larry Lehman.
I'm here at the End of life Committee and
great to be here.
We had a Brenda's committee and our
committee had a great meeting together
last week and I look forward to sharing
some of that.
Thank you.
Appreciate that.
And then, of course, Chris Biskowski.
Morning, everybody.
Chris Discuski here.
I'm a veteran and no longer I'm a chair
propagation committee,
but we've largely wrapped up our work.
So I'm just here to support everybody
else.
Yes, thank you very much.
And you're right,
the the rule setting had gone through for
the last 1 and I know we'll get to that
through updates from the program in a
little bit.
And now on to program staff.
And so doctors are well,
if you wanted to introduce everybody and
and let from your team and let them share.
Good morning everyone.
Thank you.
And just to to keep it a little shorter,
I'll just go through and introduce the
Department of Health team members.
So to start, we have Jorge Gonzalez,
who is our psilocybin program manager.
We have Cyrus Ratman,
who is our environmental scientist,
Leslie Peterson, our compliance Officer,
Johnny Moshe, who is, well,
his official title is management analyst,
but he is really the glue that keeps us
all together administratively and will be
helping us out today.
We have Doctor Robert Truckner,
our medical director.
We have Celina Montoya,
who is our finance director and who is
here to help and assist down the road as
we start looking at things such as how we
handle payments with regard to equity
fund,
not that we're talking about that today,
but so she has a good idea as well of
what's happening.
We have Adrian Estrada,
who is one of our health educators,
and I think that is all of our current
team members that are here today.
I'm just double checking to make sure I
didn't miss anyone.
But yes,
that is everyone that we have on online
from the program today.
So thank you.
Thank you, Don appreciate that.
And just a second,
we'll get an update from the program in a
bit.
So just to go over the agenda.
And also by the way,
please let me know when Ian Dunn gets on
and so that he can then take over to the
chair position too.
So just give me a heads up,
tell me to stop talking our agenda today,
we will hear from the program and the
updates that are have happened and coming
up in the future.
We've got a couple of potential
recommendations, one on clinical roles.
And there also was one that I saw come
from another committee that we'll share a
little bit with patient qualification
safety committee,
which did have some committee
consolidated recommendations.
And again, begins here.
I'll let him present, but otherwise,
I'll kind of share and we'll be able to
have discussion on that.
And then we'll have updates from the
other committees and hear from report
outs from them,
any other business that might take place.
And then we'll set our next meeting date
and location.
We'll move into public comment at the end,
and that'll allow anybody to up there 3
minutes to kind of share whatever you'd
like.
So to move on to the next part of the
agenda updates from the program.
So Don, anything you'd like to share?
Thank you, Dan.
Really right now,
things are moving along on schedule where
things have been happening pretty
smoothly for the most part.
And and that really is due to all of the
participation from the board members from
the community,
and we really appreciate that.
And I just want to let everybody know
that I am very grateful that we have as
many people participating and providing
information and feedback because that's
really what's going to make this program
in the long run.
So thank you to everybody on that.
And really the other update that we have
is just that we did have back on the 24th
of April,
we did have the rule hearing for the
cultivation and testing rules.
And so those are continuing to move
forward.
We have not yet gotten the report back
from the hearing officer.
So until we do and until we have that,
we don't have any additional progress on
that front.
But we do anticipate receiving that in
the next, within the next couple of weeks.
And once we do have that,
then we will take it to the next step.
And that essentially is if the hearing
officer has said yes,
that these rules do fit in with the with
regard to the statute and are reasonable,
then we can move forward with propagating
them which or promulgating them rather.
As you can tell,
I've been looking at cultivation quite a
bit lately,
but with sending those on out and then
going into effect once they do go into
effect,
we are working on what the applications
will look like and how those will be
handled with regard to cultivators and
testing facilities or laboratories,
those those are outlined within the rule.
But we have to get the practical side set
up.
And so the practical side is we will be
doing this all through digital means,
so online.
And so once we have the rules have been
promulgated,
then we will be setting that on up
including dates.
Our anticipation is that we will be able
to start receiving applications with
regard to cultivators and testing labs by
about the middle of July.
Now again,
that does depend on if the hearing
officer states whether the rules are
appropriate or not.
If the hearing officer, by the way,
says that no,
we need to go back and do additional
major revisions on the rules,
then we will do so.
And then we will go go through the
process with the committee's and the
board and then have another rule hearing.
So just so everybody is clear,
those are the two different potential
pathways.
So as we have more information,
we'll bring it to either the committee's
and to this board depending on when the
meetings are.
So,
but that's essentially the big update
that I have from our side.
Jorge,
is there anything in particular you would
like to announce as well?
No, not at this moment.
All right.
So thank you everybody.
Are are there questions from the board
for the program?
Nope.
OK, back to you then Dan.
And and it does look like Ian has not
been able to join.
We have message to him.
So,
but what I would say is if you do want to
hold off on the review of the clinical,
maybe it might be good to do the updates
from the committee's might just be my
recommendation.
Sure we can.
We can move that to updates from the
committee's ahead of that and then we
will,
I'm very happy to kind of share what has
been coming out from,
I believe it was from the dosage
administration Clinical Practice
committee and then the patient
qualification of safety committee.
Those updates from from Ian's team too.
So I,
I don't mind taking that if he doesn't
come in by that time.
So perfect.
No problem.
Then let's go ahead and I'll let any of
the, the, the board members that chair,
any of the subcommittees just go ahead
and we'll just kind of do it as a round
Robin.
So whoever would like to go first,
please go ahead and unmute,
and whoever speaks first will go first.
OK, fine.
Hi,
this is from the Equity Access and
Cultural considerations of committee.
We met, I wanna say a couple weeks ago,
we have a a new meeting on the 19th and I
think it was the 13th that we met.
No, the 6th, sorry,
the 6th I days and everything is blurring
in together with me.
But we met it was in person.
So hopefully we can get another in person
as we move along.
And that was a hybrid.
So you could you could also zoom in and
meet in person.
And it was a building here in Santa Fe.
So what we had from that committee,
we were able to establish and this is not,
this is this has not yet reached the
board just yet.
We still have some more meetings to kind
of solidify this.
But we established A baseline for a scale
to start from to hand over to the DoH to
look at,
to kind of give some scaling numbers.
And what I mean by that,
this is where I was saying like the math
of the math nerds and everybody else,
what we're looking at is just the, the,
the baseline for.
For the poverty line,
the baseline for like how we would be
able to help anyone who is interested in
participating with the equity fund.
So this is for the equity fund.
And at this point we were looking at 200%
poverty line.
So I can't remember anything that was
like roughly 5160,
some $1000 a year annually.
And those reason why you're using the
percentages is so that that can fluctuate
based on income etcetera.
And as that moves,
because it's based on the federal poverty
line as a starting point.
And then we were trying to cap it around
600% of that.
So after 600%,
a person would be responsible for paying
for a full cost of treatment.
Now there's a lot of other variables
involved.
And so if anyone like actually is able to
kind of wrap their head around what that
means, you know, great.
But basically it's just, you know,
within the 200% out of 600% based on the
incomes,
trying to find within there the different
scale for how much of the equity fund
might be able a participant might be able
to get.
So there's a lot of math involved.
I don't want to like give too much away,
but just if you have the mental capacity
to wrap your head around these things,
please come to the Equity Access and
Cultural Considerations meetings.
We have a presentation set for next week
to talk about these things and what that
could look like.
We have a lot of different variables,
but right now we're just basing it on
income, income for now.
And then we'll start adding in all the
other potential variables, which could be,
you know, an access to the equity fund,
which could be for caregivers,
for childcare interpreters and that sort
of thing.
And those variables will then, you know,
move that needle a little bit as to how a
person might be able to access the equity
fund.
Another thing to consider was just the
amount of people that this equity fund
could be able to provide money for,
whether it's like, you know,
just a handful of people and being able
to really solidly help help them versus
maybe stretching that money a little bit
more.
So again,
if anybody is interested in numbers and
equal access to funds that we have
available to us at $630,
000 for the equity fund that we're trying
to figure out the best way and the most
amount of people,
but also to do it the right way to do it
as equitably as possible.
So that's our big push right now.
And then we'll start dealing with when we
have the access.
We're also waiting on a tribal liaison.
We're also waiting on a Native
sovereignty leaders council,
public council leaders to be able to kind
of get, get a,
a gathering of everyone together so we
can actually talk about other parts of
what equity access and cultural
considerations really looks like.
But right now it's the the biggest goal
is to look how to to cut up that equity
fund for people.
So again,
everyone come to help figure that out on
the meeting on Tuesday at 3:00.
Thank you.
Desma.
Is there anybody from the board that
wanted to any questions or anything for
Desma's team?
Thank you.
Appreciate it.
And who would like to go next?
Which committee?
Well,
I'm going to drag Larry in with this and
so Larry and I can talk about what our
meeting was all about last time was end
of life committee.
What was is the committee or is it?
Yeah, the end of the life committee.
And you know what is, you know,
what does training look like?
What is, you know,
what is everybody's position and role?
Larry, you can jump in at any time.
I'm just gonna ramble and then you can
jump in.
But it was pretty.
It was, it was really good.
I really enjoyed it because I think what
happens to all of us is that we get into
our silos and, you know, we're there.
We're working on things and this was
really very eye opening for for me to to
see how Larry's group is coming up around
to all of these different aspects that
could be in the education and training
committee.
Because I think this is a part that
doesn't get a whole lot of attention as
far as therapists go.
Like myself,
I don't have any training in end of life
or the quality of the life that that
people are experiencing during their time
when when it's ending.
So this was a very important part of this
education and training.
And I think that should be added into
probably one of the competency curriculum
that's there because, you know,
there's just so much to touch on,
but this is, I think one of the,
one of the most important ones to learn
about.
Thanks, Brenda.
I,
I can drop in a little bit of information
about one of the areas that we focused on.
Can anyone put my slides up there and
send you guys the slides?
1 area that's come up a lot with end of
life is just, you know,
how do we have the roles for non licensed
providers?
How do we have models if assuming that
it's there's going to be at home care?
And so we've, you know,
have have a couple of different thoughts
that we've shared that in our group and
we shared with Brenda's committee and I
was gonna try to show just a few slides
of few slides of that.
We'll have that up for you in just a
minute, Larry.
OK, OK.
I I can fill up the space tool then.
So, So what we're,
what we've looked at is really the idea
of that there may be two potential ways
for non licensed providers to,
to be able to be involved in, in this.
And one of them is a role that it could
be what we would call a facilitator role,
but it's not a facilitator role that's
licensed as it is in Colorado and Oregon.
OK, good.
We have the slides here and if you want
to flip those into slideshow mode,
that'd be great.
But otherwise it's just fine.
SO11 recommendation from the end of life
community is that everybody that's
involved in end of life psychedelic care
have at least 28 hours of training
specific to end of life care.
And that could potentially occur during
people's core training.
But the feedback we've gotten is that
that much doesn't usually happen.
And we think that the, you know,
as Brenda mentioned,
the competencies for end of life are can
be somewhat unique.
They can involve other areas,
but palliative care, spiritual.
Here, So that was one recommendation.
You know what came through that is some
clarification and Adam was very helpful
there at the meeting of the role of the
lead practitioner and then ways to
proposing roles for assistant to the lead
practitioner.
And we we see that there's two different
roles that could be assistance.
Next slide.
So just just to remind us all like,
you know, the lead practitioner, you know,
as defined by the bill of the regs really
is limited to certain groups here.
And so the the issue is how can other
people get get involved there?
I would skip to the next slide.
Actually, it's a little more up to date.
So one idea is, you know,
the trained lead practitioner from non
clinical or community based pathways and
the idea that there could be a non
licensed facilitator that could be
participating under the license of the
license provider.
And we we have several ways of this seem
to be relevant to end of life care.
It could be a somebody who's a death
doula.
It could be a chaplain,
other spiritual role or a legacy provider,
someone who's been doing this work for,
you know, perhaps decades,
but will not be able to become unlicensed.
They also could potentially have a full
150 hour training similar to what people
happen in Oregon, Colorado.
But it would also would be very
appropriate to have that non licensed
facilitator have recognition for prior
trainings and experience.
Next slide.
We also looked at like a, you know,
a more limited role of assistance and you
know,
part of it we realized that there needs
to be two people,
especially if there's going to be at home
care and one of them would be the license
provider.
But we're trying to develop a role that
can be somebody that's more of an
assistant there.
We came up the role and I want to give
credit for this name to Hanifa Washington,
the space attendant role supporting
psychedelic assisted care at the end of
life.
And this could be some someone that works
there of supporting the license, you know,
practitioner of the client and family
members.
The actual training for this could be
relatively limited.
We thought it could be like a 40 hour
training,
a 4050 hour where half of that would be
on end of life care.
And for the other half,
we thought modeling something after Zendo,
which is dealing with emergency
psychedelic care and people could get
that training.
So that could potentially be 40 to 50
hours.
Again, it's a non license role,
but one that we could you know be very
supportive and be certainly make it
easier to have two people in the home
without having to have the expense of two
licensed people.
Next slide Well,
qualifications a little bit like for this
space attended training could be
completion of a psychedelic center,
peer support such as endo supervised
practicum or direct experience.
So preferred and other training there and
then whatever state requires
certification that we're suggesting for
end of life training.
This person.
We think when we're dealing with the
areas like a Hospice care that we're
optimistic that they actually could be a
volunteer that there are a lot of people
do want to do volunteering in Hospice and
end of life work.
And so it could be that role.
There also can be like a stipend stipend
role.
We can see a lot of people that may be
interested in in this role.
People could be doing that, you know,
that are potentially retired or people
could also be doing this as sort of a way
of getting exposure to the space.
There may be before that's a little bit
of a pun exposure to the space right
before they decide to get more of an
advanced training.
So that would be another role for this
this person.
Next slide.
We also were recognizing you know that
you know that there's also besides the
people that are licensed or assisting
client directed family members that
spiritual providers or chaplains.
You may not have training to be only a
practitioner death duelist.
You may decide not to be trained as a
facilitator,
only a practitioner and other people and
that all these folks are potential
members of the care team.
So we we talked about a lot of other
stuff with with Brendan committee,
but I thought this would be interesting
as people will start looking at, you know,
the other indications like who might be
appropriate for other members of the care
team for the other indications.
So thanks for thanks for listening.
Thank you, Larry,
thank you for taking the lead role on
this.
And, you know,
describing what was said in the meetings
and yeah, the Zendo project is,
is another one that really attends to
people who are in distress,
especially for, you know,
when people are experiencing adverse
effects.
And Dan,
I wanted to tell you also that in your
meeting,
when I was attending your meeting, I mean,
you real really got into the nuts and
bolts of.
Exactly what is done in, in attending,
you know, a patient.
So I'm,
I'm really just in awe of all of the work
that, that, you know,
everyone is doing here because as far as
education and training goes,
this is gonna be degraded and the,
you know,
the core competency roles that everybody
needs to do.
So it's going to really build a real
robust curriculum,
I think for a lot of people.
And I think around 150 hours,
we want to try to align that with
Colorado and Oregon.
And I know,
but that would be from start to finish
for someone that that had that wants to
learn about how to do this kind of work
that would I see as I'm looking at all of
this information would be really
appropriate and aligned.
That's my opinion.
But you know,
we'll see what the DoH decides at the end
here.
But as far as reciprocity and all of that
goes,
I think having like a core competency for
the reciprocity and then have Ling like
an A la carte type of thing for people
that that do qualify for all the core
competencies.
But just want to add on or have more of a,
a better foundation for here in New
Mexico.
And I think I was mentioning it last time,
especially for for practicing the initial,
you know,
practicum of everything that needs to be
done.
Because a lot of people have been kind of
sitting with their with their
certifications from Oregon,
Colorado and California.
They're all sitting on it and just
waiting for to see what we're going to be
doing in DoH.
And another thing that I see happening is
a lot of people are wondering, you know,
what their roles are as far as unlicensed
Co facilitators, guides,
space holders or whatever we call them at
the end here.
They're, they're really wondering and I,
I really try to tell people, you know,
hey, come to these meetings,
you really know what's happening here as
far as that's concerned,
because I think what's happening is
people are having groups and talking
about all of this,
but they're not really seeing what we're
doing here.
So I, you know,
anybody that's fresh and new to this,
this meeting,
I really encourage them to look over our
past recordings or past meetings and get
caught up on what we're trying to do here,
because I think a lot of people feel like
they're getting left out.
But really we want to, we,
we want Co facilitators,
we want that they're to support the
practitioners that are licensed.
And I think that's all I have to say
right now.
Thank you, appreciate that, both of you.
Thank you very much Brendan and Doctor
Lehman for sharing.
Before you walk away from this stuff,
please share if you have upcoming
meetings for either or a combined from
your teams,
if you have your dates already planned or
anything like that.
Oh yeah.
I I have one on the 22nd and if anyone
wants from the board wants to join in
that meeting and participate in the core
competencies.
It seems like I'm kind of going over the
same information all the time,
but it gets a little meatier as we get go
along because we have to kind of add more
things into this and,
and usually it's just a curriculum that
we are looking at.
And I know there are many teachers out
there for psychedelic therapy.
What that's going to look like for New
Mexico.
We're just trying to make it our own and
make it as equitable and fair as possible.
And I think if anybody from the board
wants to join in on that meeting that
that's fine with me.
I'm just going to be going over the same
information.
OK, thank you.
And Doctor Leven, you're muted as well.
So if you wanted to.
Sure, thank you.
We,
we've heard end of life committee is on
June 5th is our is our next time from
1:00 to 3:00.
And yeah, I'd love to have people join.
I think one of our focus is maybe
starting to talk about issues of
prioritizing.
We we've talked about how we have a very
expensive view of end of life that might
include someone who, you know, has many,
many years to live.
But as we started thinking about limited,
limited funds in the equity fund,
I think that we want to open up the
discussion to see how we would look at is
there like an appropriate way to to
prioritize people for that.
And so ultimately,
that's what that that may be a great
thing for our groups to kind of link up
on.
Thank you.
Thank you, Sir.
I appreciate that.
And Don, I saw your hand go up.
Thank you.
Dan.
I was just going to let everybody know
that I had put the meeting notes in the
chat and apparently I may have just been
a split second faster than Chris.
So thank you to Chris also for also
posting it.
But that does list all of the currently
scheduled meetings that we have at this
time.
So if anybody wants to check them on out
and register for them,
you can just click on those links and go
to their individual pages for those
meetings.
Perfect.
Thank you.
Then I'll give a share out from our
research and continuous improvement
committee.
We had met last week and had a really
good discussion.
We've got some wonderful people that are
been working on work groups including
Doctor James Brown and Gregory Evans,
Danielle Leonard,
Eileen Brewer and have been doing and I
think Doctor Linda for Timmy have been
doing some work as well,
doing a lot of work when it comes to
would try to focus a lot on patient fits
and and, and facilitator fit,
focus on safety and reporting and data.
And so for our last work group,
what we decided to do is to really refine
our responsibilities for the RACI
committee to ensure that we we work well
with the other subcommittees and know
kind of where our bright lines are,
where we kind of stop and where we can
provide best reflection back but also
receive instruction from.
So our three responsibilities we aligned
on where the reporting framework we
needed to come up with the reporting
framework first,
because this is all centered around
safety.
We wanted to make sure that we have
patient safety and patient data at our
heart of this.
Second responsibility is harm reduction
and a quality improvement framework.
And the third responsibility is the core
and extended data set framework.
And so by starting with our reporting
ideas first,
working back through the harm reduction
and quality improvement,
we'll finally land on the data set
framework that we needed to have to
support that.
So we I've broken into three kind of
intersessional work groups.
So between our monthly meetings,
we have one that will focus on the care
pathway and safety.
We'll have one that focuses on the
participant experience and fit.
And then the last one will be more of the
data, the data and reporting architecture.
So we've kind of aligned around the, the,
the,
the shared journey that a participant
will go through from the first stage of
preparation into session,
into integration and into an oversight or
review framework.
And so that kind of puts everything
around asking Are you ready,
how are you doing?
What happened?
And also is anything wrong?
And so the wonderful thing is that the
team has identified a large a battery of
different protocols that exist that are
research based,
that are vetted and are in the research
here.
So by utilizing those,
we're now they're aligning around how
much of that is done by the participant,
how much is done by the clinician or
facilitator and and on.
So therefore they're working on that
aspect.
But kind of what we wanted to do around
those five parts of the journey is to ask
questions like what should be happening
at this stage,
what risk or concerns arise at this stage,
What should be documented,
what should be monitored and reviewed,
And what belongs in a core versus
extended data set so that that way we can
focus on the core data set,
which will be important for ensuring
program compliance and safety monitoring.
And then of course,
quality improvement is needed in the end.
But there's also an extended data set
that would be wonderful if there is the
ability to,
especially focusing on research.
And so we wanted to align that so that
that way we don't have people that are
looking at it thinking like this is way
too much to have to put in for every
single time we wanted to have here's the
core.
So again,
that will be kind of the last thing that
we'll work on.
We do have meetings that are coming up,
our June 12th meeting.
We always have this from 9:00 until 11.
So on June 12th,
that's when our reporting framework will
come out.
We'll kind of align around that to get a
consensus.
Then on July 10th will be our harm
reduction and quality improvement
consensus.
So that will be presented and then we'll
work towards making sure we can solidify
that.
And August 7th will be the core slash
extended data set consensus.
So hopefully we can get on this kind of
regular monthly cadence.
And so if you're interested in doing
intercessional work between them,
of course,
informing and learning more about it,
please join any of those meetings so that
you can kind of hear.
And of course, intercessional work.
I always said like from my teaching
background was like, OK,
you get homework to do.
And so it gives me a lot of homework to
do in the back end.
But it's great because the team has done
an outstanding job of finding what tools
and protocols that are out there that
like I said,
our research base did not kind of gut
feeling.
So it's been wonderful to try to focus
around the idea of patient safety when we
do this.
So once patients have been qualified and
they're going through,
we really wanted to make sure that the
system is is centered around the patients
and again,
the best fit and the care for the
patients.
So and that is it for the Ricey's
subcommittee.
I do know that on our agenda,
we do have some recommendations and I
believe that the I believe it was the
patient qualification and safety
committee or the clinical roles.
I believe yes, yes,
then I do have that and I can bring that
up.
Dominic, go ahead and finish.
I was just going to say the the other
recommendations are still in process and
because the board had determined earlier
that they weren't going to be looking at
petitions for new conditions until after
the program had started up,
I believe it was either like next
February or March.
So I would say we can hold off on those.
But if we move forward with the clinical,
I do know the one that I received out of
the patient qualification safety
committee was simply a tier clinical
support framework,
meaning the the qualifications of
patients that fit one of those 4 already
agreed upon standards,
then their their specific medical
backgrounds were broken into four
different tiers for standard support.
Enhanced clinical support does that.
I do have it out as well.
So that does go more into the guideline
side rather than regulations.
So what I would recommend is looking as
far as on the clinical roles,
which just as a as a note,
that was really it's not the clinical
role portion isn't for adoption by the
board because that's still being looked
at by the training and education and end
of life.
It was more just pure sort of how it's
starting and how things are moving
forward.
But we wanted to make sure and and I know
Ian wanted to make sure that those got,
you know, at least the discussion started.
Perfect.
That'll be great.
And so we'll go ahead and have this
presentation and then the discussion,
but we won't,
I don't know if we should take there's no
action to be taken on this, correct.
OK, great.
Just so that I can be clear on this, so,
and again,
this is speaking on behalf of that
subcommittee.
So please understand that I don't know a
lot of the answers from anything on this.
And if there are any questions,
I believe that that would probably be
best suited for that, that work group.
But and, and Brenda,
I know that this will probably be very
closely with your committee as well.
So please feel free to jump in with
anything on there.
And it's on the screen and also in the
notes and the chat as well for anybody to
read if you cannot read from the screen
there.
So just I'll go, yes, go.
Yeah, yeah, Dan.
So I want,
I'm going to try to attend every one of
your meetings.
So I'm there to see how this is being
formed.
So all the clinical roles here are
aligned with what clinicians do.
And also too, I think, you know, if I can,
I've been looking at a lot of your
information and at Larry's information
and I want to kind of mesh the two
together.
But I don't want to start doing that just
yet because we still have to look at some
of these things as you know, these are,
you know, qualifications that.
You know,
all therapists meet in order to keep
their license.
So but I love the I love the way it's the
the details of this.
So I may go ahead and, and if permission,
take some of your information and also
with Larry's information and,
and try to formulate something here in
the next meeting just to show the public
what exactly what clinicians are doing
here as far as education and training
goes.
Because it, it, it,
it's this is the education and training
part is really the boring part for the,
for the general public because they're
not practitioners.
So this is geared more towards, you know,
the,
the learning and training part for Co
facilitators and anyone that's licensed.
So looking at this, I'm,
I'm going to just kind of like put some
things here and there in my next
presentation, but it shouldn't,
like I said before,
it's going to be more of the same
information that's going to be presented
to the public.
Sure, absolutely.
And this is coming from the dosage
administration and clinical practice
subcommittee.
So, so therefore, you know, that'll be,
you know, Ian subcommittee.
So definitely,
if there's anything on that you all can
work together on, please do so.
Again,
I'm just kind of reporting out what was
shared here and this will hopefully help
us to to see where these different roles
are.
So one of the notes on here you you can
read on the screen of course,
but the qualified individual could be
fulfilling multiple roles where a scope
and credentialing allow.
So the first role that was presented was
the clinician,
which would be a psilocybin serpaline
clinician and this is defined in iMac.
It should be a licensed clinician acting
within their own their scope of practice
with the diagnostic authority and so
listing out different credentials there
including LPCCMDMDO responsibilities.
The person this role will be identifying
potential candidates based upon the
qualifying condition.
Right now, as Doctor Owen said,
we have 4 certain qualifying conditions
for entry or certified qualifying
conditions for entry into the program.
Share relevant diagnostic and clinical
history with the patient consent in
accordance with applicable privacy laws.
Limitations mean that certification does
not constitute clinical clearance.
Not responsible for determining medical
appropriateness or dosing or safety
planning or administration decisions.
And so the recommendation that was made
for education training.
So it's established the minimum education,
continuing AD and licensure requirements.
Define required competencies.
And so that's that specific role.
Then that's what that role would take
place in the psilocybin medical
psilocybin program.
The next role is the practitioner.
This would be a psychedelic therapist
defined in in Mac as well.
The scope This role is to conduct the
comprehensive biopsychosocial assessment,
review medical psychiatric substance use
history,
identify contraindications and medical
interactions,
evaluate risk for psychological or
physiological response,
and create a safety plan.
A set and assess support system.
Determine the medical appropriateness for
psilocybin treatment.
The responsibilities in this role are to
evaluate clinical appropriateness for
psilocybin use, including,
but not limited to medication
interactions,
medical and mental health history,
and current functioning.
If the patient is not appropriate,
then refer them to a primary care
provider or an appropriate treatment
avenue.
Using trauma informed and cultural
culturally competent communication
throughout the screening and treatment
process.
Assign a clinical support tier,
established dosing parameters or
considerations,
approve or defer participation based upon
safety and must be involved in
psychological preparation.
The limitations for this role does not
provide facilitation unless specifically
credentialed and does not conduct
preparation or integration unless duly
trained.
So the recommendation to the Education
and Training Committee to establish
minimum education and licensure
requirements,
define required competencies and
assessments and contraindication review
interventions, medication interaction,
screening,
risk stratification and harm reduction.
And the last role that has been defined
is the facilitator role.
Facilitator is an individual who has
completed department approved training
and education,
has been registered with the department,
whose role is limited to providing non
clinical support and presence to a
patient preparing for,
experiencing the effects of,
or integrating the effects of
administration as allowed by the program.
A facilitator does not perform and shall
not be construed to perform clinical
assessments, diagnosis, treatment,
or any other act constituting the
practice of medicine, nursing,
or any other licensed health profession.
A facilitator does not act under the
supervision, direction,
or authority of any licensed health care
provider,
and no provider shall be deemed to have
supervisory responsibility over
facilitator solely by virtue of their
concurrent participation in any part of
the program.
Their responsibilities include to conduct
administrative.
I'll just let it scroll just a little bit
up.
All right, here we go.
Responsibilities including conducting the
administrative preparation and
integration sessions in coordination with
a psychedelic psychedelic therapist to
obtain informed consent from the patient,
support patient during administration
session.
Monitor the psychological and physical
safety during those sessions.
Escalate any medical or psychological
concerns to the psychedelic therapist or
appropriate emergency services.
Prepare materials for patients self
administration in accordance with
approved protocols and psychedelic
therapist direction and document session
activities.
The limitation of this role does not
determine medical appropriateness
independently and does not override
Contra and addictions or safety
restrictions.
And the recommendation to the Education
Training Committee is to establish
minimum education continuing yet and
licensure requirements and to define
required competencies.
So I, I know that in the chat,
and we'll get to the chat in a little bit.
There was a question,
would the document be made available for
future reference?
And since this is probably going to be
just a recommendation to a committee,
I believe that there might be some,
this might be included in the notes
section on the website once this gets
posted up there.
Thank you for recommending that.
So I'm going to let Brenda speak to these
first since this does have complete
alignment in with her committee.
So anything that strikes you and then
we'll open it up to everybody else also.
Thank you, Dan.
Yeah.
So this is pretty standard clinical
practices,
you know that even though this is a
little different because we are working
with psilocybin and Sosin,
this is part of the, you know,
integrated to the,
the the program and making sure that
safety is,
is paramount to everything that we're
doing.
I think it's done very well and can it
can be included into the core practices
of a clinician that's doing this work.
So it's it's dead on.
I mean, I don't really see anything else.
However, I want to include, you know, any,
any indigenous or tribal in in that as
well and how that would be part of the
core competencies as well.
And, and have that as part of that.
And,
and that's about the only thing I I see
that needs to be included in this and how,
how that would look like.
I do have something written up.
I can't recall what it is,
but I do have AI think a little segment
and and another core competency that I'm
working on right now to have that as a
part of this as well.
So that safety and dosage and all of that
is also in included in all of this.
So that's about the only thing I I see
that needs to be included.
But I think this is being very careful
about, you know,
how we're treating people,
how these assessments are done,
making sure they are properly educated
and prepared for this treatment.
The other things are, again,
I think collecting the data is really,
really important because I think that
there's, from what I understand,
like all the journals that I've read and
you know, the, you know, the,
the tracking of all of this, this,
this looks really, really very,
very meaty.
I, I don't know,
I'm trying to find the right word for it,
but it,
it has a lot of really good information
that can be used in future research.
So I think as far as qualifying
conditions go for a patient,
that will be very,
very important because the more we look
at this data and to see how people are
responding to the medication.
I think the outcomes of what is going to
be taken from all of this information is
going to be really important not only for
the researchers,
but also for the patient too.
Because the more they know about how they
are responding to the medication is going
to be really important for their healing
and getting better.
So I think this is, this is just,
this is just culminating and, and,
and getting to, to things that I,
I think a lot of places only like,
you know, maybe some,
some colleges may be doing that for some
research purposes,
but I think this is going to be even
bigger than we even expect it to be.
So, Dan,
I think you and your group have been
doing a lot of really wonderful work here
that I, that I haven't seen before.
And, and just so this is,
this is Ian's work group on the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee.
So I'm just I'm just reporting out from
from from that since Ian's not here here
to get to some of the questions in the
chat.
I'll go to M messes and then I'll move up.
And that said,
asked so psychedelic therapist can't
cannot provide psychedelic therapy prep
admin integration.
That term choice seems strange for what
like seems like a triage screening role,
meaning I don't know the specific answer
to the the terminology used.
However,
I will say the note is a single qualified
individual should be allow to fulfill
multiple roles where scope,
training and credentialing allow then
going up the chain to miss it there.
Eileen Schummels,
what is the nuances between the
facilitator and space attendant mentioned
earlier?
And so Doctor Lehman mentioned the space
role and to and I will quickly say that
it fits into the facilitator role and
definition there,
but Doctor Lehman might want to share a
little bit more specific.
Sure.
Yeah,
we we're thinking the space attendant
could have less training honestly that
the the space attendant could be someone
with a 40 hour training and that would
just focus on the emergency training in
the zendo and the training friend of life
care.
So we're viewing that as potentially
significantly shorter training than for a
facilitation.
Thank you.
And to hit some of the other comments
that happened after that,
Eileen Schimmel said, again,
I appreciate the detail in the document,
but also worry about the terms clinician
and practitioner.
Those terms are often used
interchangeably and it might help to have
more to distinguish them.
James Brown,
can you expand on the reciprocity piece
and your thoughts on who will be able to
apply for a permit?
And Joan Manuel R Ruko,
will naturopathic doctors indeed,
who are similarly licensed as primary
care providers under New Mexico law and
are ultimately trained in whole person
and plant based medicine also be
exclusive explicitly included in that
definition?
So to hit some of those questions to
John's question,
I believe that the best outlet for that
question would be to attend the dosage
Administration and Clinical Practice
committee,
since this is a document that came from
that to make sure that that would be
something that the committee does here to
James Brown.
Can you expand on the reciprocity piece?
And so that would really be a Brenda
question when it comes to education and
training.
And Eileen,
same thing on the clinician versus
practitioner.
Those terms are used interchangeably.
And so again going back to the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee would be where that might be
brought up.
So that that way Ian and the worst of the
work group could ensure that there is a
specific definition of those kind of
things, clinician and practitioner,
so that we can make sure that the the
vocabulary, the definitions are clear.
Even though other programs and,
and colloquially we might use those terms
interchangeably.
We want to make sure that in the medical
psilocybin program that those are clearly
defined and used consistently throughout.
So I hope that helps answer those
questions.
I know it's not an answer to the question,
unfortunately,
it's just I can't answer them here myself
and we don't have the committee chair
here to answer those.
And Brent, go ahead.
Just just to answer James,
James's question about reciprocity and
what that will look like.
So we're looking at about 10 to 20 hours
of you know this state regulatory
compliance and cultural humility in New
Mexico communities,
legacy and lineage and reciprocity,
integration,
ethical and scope of practice of
alignment and safety and risk alignment.
And you know, those who will be eligible.
We're hoping that anyone that's had any
previous training from a CISCIIS and
Naropa maps,
Intertrec and a host of other places that
people have gotten training.
Hopefully the DoH will accept a lot of
their the training and the certification
from those places,
especially Oregon and Colorado also.
And I include that in the reciprocity for
those that have been trained and we this
would be just an add on like 10 to 20
hours for here in New Mexico.
So we're can get practitioners and
clinician clinicians and other other
people who qualify with a license and to
be streamlined into this.
And we will go through that training
first.
This is what I'm imagining as the DoH
finds fit for the core competencies.
And then you know, take we,
we haven't really discussed an exam or
anything like that because that would
have to be some type of program that
would have to be constructed.
And then getting, getting licensed,
we haven't gone there yet.
We're still kind of waiting for all of
that.
So any licensed,
I'm just going to say practitioner for
right now,
or anyone that's licensed can do the
reciprocity that can show some kind of
certification or if you are a,
a legacy healer, maybe a, a,
a letter from your community showing that
you, you have these core competencies.
Whatever we decide what that will be.
And there's a,
there's a lot of different things here,
but making sure that, you know,
safety is paramount to everything that we
are doing here as far as reciprocity goes.
And a lot another question that comes up
like, OK,
so let's say we have all that in place.
Where is where is this going to be taught?
You know,
how much money is going to be allotted
for teachers?
What are the materials are going to look
like and how is this all going to roll
out?
So, you know,
we still have a lot of work to do in in
the nuts and bolts with that.
But as far as reciprocity goes,
I'm looking at 10 to 20 hours and and
that also includes the practitioner,
you know,
getting some hands on experience.
But then again,
we have this other thing where, OK,
where are those patients going to come
from if we're trying to do, you know,
the the practice of using psilocybin
medicine?
So there's, there's a lot,
there's a little bit of working out there,
but I think we can work on that a little
bit more and see where that come comes to
fruition.
Thank you.
Thank you, Brent, I appreciate it.
And Desma, go right ahead.
So I think this is like a lot of trying
to take notes,
so I'm apologize for kind of jumping
around here.
I do have a question of clarification for
Dominic and the rest of the group because
something was said early on about
recommendations and guidelines and I just
kind of wanted to gloss over that really
quickly.
But then also just more to Brenda's point
about getting more input about the tribes
and, and that my suggestion,
and this is open to everybody else,
is that when we are kind of coming to
these places in our different committees,
that if if if I'm not able to attend or
for, you know, back and forth,
like just making sure that, yeah,
we can present, you know,
that this specific thing in the committee
language, you know,
has gone over and we've kind of asked.
In that way,
and I know we're kind of sort of waiting
for some feedback from tribal liaison and
the public council governors as well.
And to that point specifically,
at least this is just my opinion and my
understanding,
it would be probably a point to make sure
that you know, that the door,
it's more to me like the door is open
that we have the understanding that
because tribal sovereignty is important
to saying this is, you know,
something that we have available to you.
Should you want to adopt what this what
the work that we've done in this
particular instance.
And then make it work for your tribe and
make it working according to what you
feel is best for your for your people.
And of course,
that takes kind of more of like a
diplomacy aspect of it and again,
tribal sovereignty and, you know,
maybe some more liaising with that to
kind of understand like what would be the
best way to to approach that On the other
side of that,
knowing for sure that we have people such
as myself, you know,
not living on tribal land.
And what does that look like whenever I
am going into a facility and working with
a facilitator who is here in Santa Fe or
in Albuquerque or places that are on non
tribal land, Right.
So I feel like part of the idea is just
making sure that that is an awareness
that the door is open to the practitioner
or the facilitator,
whoever is working with the person,
that they are just understanding,
you know,
that they're that the person is coming in
with this cultural lens.
And and you know, and,
and also to that on the other opposite
side is, you know,
people who are city Indians and not
raised on reservations.
And the assumption that we're coming in
with all of this cultural knowledge and
teachings and understandings that we're
just like, yeah, that's foreign to me.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
So it's just it's just being open and
aware and just in general that we're a
human beings coming in with so much.
We're also very multi tribal.
So there's a lot of people who have,
you know,
five different tribes that they represent
and they're from all over the United
States.
And it may not necessarily be just from
New Mexico.
And they're coming in from Alaska,
they're coming in from Canada,
they're coming in from Bolivia,
they're coming in from different places.
So maybe it's just more that, you know,
we understand that when we're working in
culturally sensitive areas that we are
not essentially assuming anything,
but also to that it's a door open for the
tribal sovereignty aspect of it because
we have the 23 federally recognized
tribes here in in New Mexico.
But on that note,
this question does become to the
questions and to, you know,
consolidating the language that we are
gonna at some point, you know,
start making those definitions that at
the end of the year,
these are the things that are, you know,
our as meetings and hearings are adopted
and put into place.
We are going to have that narrowed
language.
We are going to have that specificity of
the definitions that we're using because
you know,
somebody who might use the word journey,
I used the word journey.
Someone might say a session or a
treatment and so forth.
So we have to be very mindful of of that
for sure.
But I feel like just making sure that we
understand that at some point we're going
to have those definitions so that we're
using them across the board and it's
gonna not be as confusing at the very end
of it when things come out of the wash.
But on that note,
this is where I have the question for
everyone else.
And just wanted to clarify, as the board,
we're making recommendations to the
Department of Health and I heard
mentioned that that's not going to be
something it could be in the guidelines.
So as we're working through this and we
have recommendations that are baseline,
then we have like our wish list
essentially of all the guidelines and
recommendations that we wish could the
people who are really wanting to,
you know, rise above just the baseline.
And I just kind of maybe wanted to
clarification,
if possible from Dominic Ann or anyone
else,
if I have that kind of understanding that
we have recommendations from the board to
the department for their consideration
into adopting.
And and then from there,
there is something else that our
guidelines are those guidelines then
going to also be like, hey,
if you want to up your game as a
practitioner or, you know, propagationist,
these are the things that we also,
you know,
you might want to be able to consider.
And I just kind of wanted to clarify that
for myself.
Sure.
Good, good morning again,
everyone and Desba,
that's a great question.
So regulations are really the things that
have to be done.
So they are items that are going to be
required.
So for example,
with regard to cultivation,
it's required that any of the the
companies that may get permitted have to
register with New Mexico tax and Rev the
business license, etcetera.
Those are requirements that have to be
done.
But the guidelines and really the correct
term is actually best practices are those
things.
And we're and that's something that we
hear all the time,
especially in medical clinical fields
where those are things that are really
set up as guidelines for providers,
clinicians,
therapists that really say here are some,
here is some guidance for around this.
But you know, each patient,
each individual is a little bit different.
You are going to have to use your
judgement and your experience to actually
see how this works with regard to the
patient.
And what that really does is it'll it
gives those individuals a little bit of a
pathway on how to determine what's going
to work.
And they may have to veer a little from
that pathway for specific individuals,
for things that, for example,
we don't know yet.
For example,
some things coming in are about how
things like SSRIs actually may have an
influence in how psilocybin uptake occurs
in the body.
And so providing some best practices
about how a clinician or a practitioner
could incorporate that into their work to
ensure safety for the patient is
important.
But we don't want to put that into a
regulation because that would then tie
the hands of someone.
And if more evidence comes out down the
road saying something like, no,
do not use that medication under any
circumstance with psilocybin,
then we would have been locked in because
of regulations.
And so that's why there is that
difference.
And this is not uncommon in the medical
world, as I mentioned,
about having those best practices,
those areas to help give direction for
those practitioners and clinicians,
but not necessarily say this is what you
must do.
And that's actually why the training and
education is so important.
But that's an example of what the best
practices are and they'll be best
practices in that area.
Best practices for things such as,
you know,
for the patients within the approved
settings,
It should be a comfortable environment.
What might that consist of?
But it doesn't mean if, for example,
we say have comfortable seating as a best
practice or places to lounge,
that sort of thing where we suddenly say,
oh, you must have a couch, a chair.
We wanna go away from that and provide.
Here are some basic thoughts and ideas.
And so that's what the difference really
is between the best practices and all of
that and that and the regulations.
Rather,
the regulations will be those things that
are absolutely required.
The best practices.
The,
the way I think of it is it's a pathway
for a,
a way forward with for the clinicians,
the providers and the patients.
So I hope that helps explain the
difference between them.
Yeah, no,
I just thank you for reiterating that.
And I just kind of wanted to point that
out because sometimes I feel, you know,
we're like, why aren't we doing this?
Or why isn't this this?
And then, you know, and it's like, OK,
we're looking for baseline.
We're looking at things that are just
like where we're at.
But it doesn't mean that, you know,
you can't make this the most best
practice and you're gonna have a hard
time keeping people out of your facility.
So I just wanted to make sure that that
was it.
Yes, yes, no.
That's why that's a really good point to
bring up because we've talked about that
before.
It's a lot of times when we talk in our
committee meetings,
we're talking a lot about best practice
and not necessary the regulation.
So it is not something that has been
decided.
It's just something that is brought up.
So it's a very,
I'm glad you brought that question up
because I think it's,
we need to also be reminded of that a lot
of times ourselves.
So and it's great to have those best
practice discussions because that's how
we can really find what, as you said,
they'll be the places that everybody
wants to be.
So at this time, I don't,
I think on our agenda we're ready to move
into any kind of public comment,
but I just wanted to double check to make
sure I don't see the agenda.
So if you might just double check my
agenda for me, please.
There we go.
So we've already the update.
So and there's I guess, go ahead, Dan.
Before we do that,
I do have an item I got reminded about
that I forgot during the program update
if that would be OK.
Absolutely.
That's the other business part.
So I just wanted to let everybody know
the department and actually all of the
various executive agencies have been
going through a process on our websites
to ensure ADA compliance,
ADA American with Disabilities Act and to
ensure compliance in all documents.
So I just wanted to let everybody know
that as the departments are going through
that,
there may sometimes be some delays and
documents being made available,
but we're working on it,
especially on documents moving forward,
ensuring that they're there and that
they're updating older documents as we
are best able to do so.
But with that in mind,
I did want to let all of the committee
chairs and board members know we may have
some guidelines with regard to
PowerPoints or other documents just to
ensure that we're following that and we
don't have to convert it later into the
ADA compliance because then that will
just take longer for us to be able to
then post items.
So just to let everybody know,
we will be putting that sending that out
to the board members just so that you're
aware and that you can use including some
templates such As for PowerPoints and
things like that.
So you don't have a lot that you have to
do on your end as well with regard to
that.
So just wanted to let you all know about
that part.
And as soon as we have those that
guidance, we'll send it out to all of you.
So thank you.
Perfect, thank you.
Great.
And we've got and then we'll go to Chris.
So Dominic,
that means no PowerPoints in Papyrus.
Our comic can yeah, we need to,
we do need to make sure that the text is
legible.
Yes.
I, I, I was thinking wing bats because,
you know,
that's the most understandable font that
there is.
So.
Oh, OK, so no PowerPoints.
I just wanted to say that I know I
realize this is really super glossed over
the Equity Access Cultural committee
report, and I didn't mean to do that.
I was just trying to get through it.
So if it sounded like I was trying to get
through it, well, that's the reason why.
So if anybody has any questions that I
could possibly answer about that more
specifically, but again,
if you didn't understand what I was
talking about and you're curious,
please come to the meetings.
That's your cue.
That's your trigger to like,
I didn't know what she was talking about.
I need to know more.
That's why you need to go to the meeting
on Tuesday.
So that's all.
Thanks, Desma.
And then Chris,
I'll be coming to your meeting on Tuesday,
does boss.
So I'm looking forward to it.
I wanted to ask the department if there's
any word on or update on when we're going
to bring in our last two board members.
Yeah, thank you, Chris.
We actually are going through the process
of doing interviews and going through
those that have come in,
those applications that have come in
since our last round had been completed
this past fall.
But if there are individuals who are on
this call right now and who are
interested,
if you go to the website and we'll get
the link here in the chat in just a
moment.
But if you go to the website,
the requirements for board members is
listed there.
There's a document on that.
And if you're interested,
I would recommend applying within
probably the next week,
give or take a little because our hope is
to get interviews finished,
it completed and finished within the next
couple of weeks and then to be able to
move those potential candidates to the
Governor's office.
So thank you, everybody, and thank you.
Great question, Chris.
And then one extra question.
We're about to go into the next.
Oh, go ahead.
Back on to Chris.
I was wondering if so we didn't,
I feel like we kind of skipped past going
over the the document there with the
clinical roles on there.
And I was wondering,
it sounded like in the training and
education meeting the other day that that
the Department of Health had kind of made
some decisions to, to amend that.
And I was wondering if we're going to get
like an updated version of that to work
with moving forward or did I misread that,
sorry.
So, so my understanding,
Chris is that that is actually a
recommendation to the Training and
Education committee as far as those
clinical roles.
And that part of what we presented in the
last meeting actually aligns for the most
part, there are some differences,
but aligns fairly well with it.
There are also have been as mentioned,
some thoughts and ideas coming from racy
from the the research committee and from
end of life.
And So what training and education that
committee is looking at.
And Brenda mentioned this is to take all
of those pieces and sort of put it
together into one final version
recommendation.
But we're not at that point yet.
And that's a part of what is going to be
happening in the next training and
education committee.
OK, I'm, I'm sorry, I think I, yeah,
not at all because that was the same
thing.
I didn't know if this was a
recommendation so that we needed to take
action on as a board, but it wasn't.
It was just something to kind of share
with the entire group.
And then of course,
if there is like AI want to make a
recommendation,
then Brenda's committee and of course,
as I've mentioned that the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee also there too.
So and so we're about to set our next
board meeting date.
And so before we do that,
I did want to ask Tomic,
is there something that for this board
that we need to look at that we need to
bring to the next board meeting in order
to make a final recommendation so that we
can move something forward?
So that way it kind of dictates the rest
of the pacing for different groups.
And when we put that date,
but not specifically yet at this point,
Dan,
the next set is going to be the training
and education piece,
as we've kind of talked about before,
but that is being developed right now.
And so I think that's really going to be
dictated by when the training and
education committee has gotten their
recommendations and that's going to take
a little bit yet.
So, and we have enough time.
We're like I had mentioned earlier,
we're actually in a good time frame and
things are moving along pretty well with
that.
So I don't think we need to say
specifically a recommendation needs to be
made at the next meeting.
However,
if there is one ready by that point,
then the board of course can act upon it.
Perfect.
And so looking at the calendar,
I know that, you know,
we're ready now at the middle of May and
looking towards the calendar we've got
towards,
if we look at the same time in the middle
of June, we have a holiday,
we have Juneteenth.
So I'm wondering would June 26th,
it's up Friday again,
doing the same kind of time work and I
don't know if it does for anybody or for
the team.
So just I'm throwing a date out to say
Friday, June 26th at 9:00 to 11:00.
And just to let you know from the
department side that it works fine.
OK,
So thank you from from y'all Doctor
Lehman says works for me.
Is there anybody that it will not work
for on the board?
OK.
June 26, Friday,
9:00 to 11:00 will be our next board
meeting.
And so Brendan,
if you do have any recommendations to
bring to the board from your team,
then we'll be able.
And if it's not,
if it's just to the point of just what
you have worked on at that point,
then we can definitely hear that as well
too.
Yeah,
it'll be just just a in a Word document
and we can go ahead and pepper it,
change it, edit,
use different language if we need to,
so that it'll be just doing one thing.
And we could just keep going back in
there and working it with with each
meeting or other committees who also I'm
gonna try to meet as many.
Unfortunately,
I can't meet despots because I haven't
everybody all my clients want to meet in
the afternoon and it's like, you know, oh,
come on, guys,
you know I've been trying to move people
overnight.
They won't budget.
So Despa, I apologize for that.
I really would love to attend your
meetings.
Yeah.
If you just want to kind of like note it
then that we can we can talk about it.
Yeah, absolutely.
And a lot of times, folks,
I can't get into the chat for some reason.
I'll, I'll log off and come back on.
And that's why you won't hear from me
because everybody's jumping in and
talking and it's like, yeah,
I want to make an appointment.
I do.
Thank you.
Get in there.
And so we've got our next date set.
And while we're about to move into the
public comment,
I will like to read some of the chat into
the public comment from the beginning of
the meeting.
And then while we're doing that,
let everybody kind of give the
instructions if you do want to speak
during public comment.
You will have 3 minutes to speak.
Make sure whenever you introduce yourself,
whenever you're giving public comment,
talk about who you are,
are you from New Mexico,
are you from somewhere else?
Do you have any affiliations?
Whenever you're ready to do that,
you can just raise your hand.
We'll call on you in order and we'll
start the timer.
We'll unmute you during that time.
So just to kind of go back while that's
happening, I'll read into the chat.
Doctor Linda Fatemi said I would like to
inform everyone of a very educational
film with heavy presence of veteran
stories, trauma,
healing and also it's going well and not
well in Oregon.
Documentary took two years to produce and
the screening will be at Santa Fe on
Saturday the 16th It's on Cocktail Cinema
and Albuquerque this Saturday,
17th or 12th, 30th and Guild.
It's also on Apple TV, Amazon Prime,
and then Brianna wonder,
thank you for sharing.
Another great film to check out.
It's a table of our own experience,
a critically pain documentary,
a table of our own,
and a link is provided.
Then the links to all the meetings were
provided after that and then into the
next set.
Senator Steinborn.
Great job, everyone.
Thank you very much, Senator,
for being here.
Gregory Evans.
Papyrus No.
And then there's the links there for the
Advisory Board application.
And now the links inside of the chat are
from Doctor Lowe about how to raise your
hands.
And so now that I have read everything in,
there should be lots of hands raised
because I've given lots of time.
That was the wait time.
I'm not seeing any hands.
That's why I'm laughing.
There we go.
I'm starting to see hands being raised.
So I'll turn it over to the DoH team then
to start to call on everybody.
And please appreciate your public comment.
All right, thanks.
And Gregory Evans, your mic is enabled.
You can unmute.
I wanted to touch on a request that Desba
made a while back for kind of a
deliverables work back schedule for each
of the committees and see if there's been
anybody working on developing something
like that so that we can visually see
what our like target deliverable window
dates might be.
So Greg, I can answer that.
That's actually something that's up to
each committee to determine what their
deliverables are.
So and I do know in different committees,
some of the committees have actually
discussed that during their committee
meetings.
So,
but there is not any master document
because really what the department is
looking at is as far as from the
regulation standpoint and working on that.
And we've kind of outlined that and that
time frame changes a little bit depending
on how much information we're getting,
how much information the committees are
getting and based upon those
recommendations.
But the overall idea is to have the
regulations with regard to the next set,
which is the training,
the education for providers, clinicians,
etcetera,
is really to have that by the end of this
summer and then with regard to locations
in the fall and that would be the
approved location.
So places applying to be facilities,
Wellness centers,
whatever terminology people would like to
utilize for that, places people do things.
Exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, I think on top of that,
I think from the contributor standpoint,
like slow,
slowly and gradually getting to the point
where we understand what a definition of
done is and versions of done because like
we're gonna deliver a thing and then it's
gonna shift and move and we're gonna
deliver a new thing.
But yeah, I think I'm a visual person.
Would just love to hear more,
more cross committee understanding of the
way the ship is moving so we're not just
floating in the water alone.
And that's all I have.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Right,
let's see next we've got Paul Walton.
And Paul,
I've enabled your mic and you can unmute
when you're ready.
Hi everyone,
Paul Walton here and firefighters for
plant medicine.
Thank you all for all the work that you
guys are doing.
This is starting to shape up and looking
really good.
I couple questions.
Let me the first question would be,
I don't know if this has been brought up
or not,
but I know we have some funding for
helping people get treatment and
everything and which is fantastic.
And I'm wondering if what the possibility
of in the future continuing some kind of
other funding so that there's kind of a
rolling, I guess,
backbone to that funding for help in the
future for people.
Because I'm sure that that money is going
to run out at some point, obviously.
But then the other question would be or
other thing that might be brought up.
And I don't know if this would be part of
the training or if it would be that with
the Department of Health.
But as facilities kind of come online for
people to go to and get treatment,
one of the things that would be really
beneficial and helpful,
I think is doing some education.
And it doesn't have to be an incredible
amount of hours or anything like that.
But just for local EMS, first responders,
law enforcement, things like that,
that might be responding to a facility
that someone's having a challenging or a
medical emergency at.
Just so that they are aware and
understanding of what is going on with
psilocybin and,
and treatment and things like that.
That would help to reduce harm to someone
that might be going through some kind of
a medical emergency or something like
that.
Because the way that we interact with
somebody definitely obviously has impact
on furthering their possible challenging
moment,
whether it be medical or with the
medicine itself.
And so I'm wondering if maybe the state
might or the Department of Health might
be interested in doing by small class or
something like that,
just for first responders to kind of help
them educate a little bit on that topic.
And then Brenda, I,
I love the a la carte thing because I
really do believe that, you know,
doing any kind of course where you're
getting certified to facilitate or
anything.
Those are just really the kind of the
core foundations.
And just like any other kind of licensure,
you kind of drift off into specialty
areas and work in things that really are
passionate with you or, or, you know,
different things like that.
So I really love that a la carte kind of
idea of doing further education and
specific areas and things like that.
And yeah,
I think that's all I really have other
than I do think it's really important to
have some kind of safety course first
facilitators.
A lot of medical therapists in different
areas like that do have CPR requirements
and stuff like that.
So I think that that some of that sort of
basic requirements should be kind of
included in those policies.
Thank you all again for everything you're
doing.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.
I just wanted to jump in real quick about
the a la carte thing.
So that's going to take a little
finessing because there's just a lot of
things that need to be,
we need to be educated on.
And like I'm trying to think of all the
pockets that could be potentially filled
with an A la carte type of thing.
So as the education and training move
along,
I'm hoping I'll have more input on what
people are needing in that type of
framework as far as the education and
training is.
Because yes, there are many,
many people in this field with
specialties and expertise and we want to
be able to try to give as much
information as possible as far as safety
and, you know, patients and concerns are.
But yeah,
and also to address what that would look
like.
So just having like a,
a core basic type of thing for right now.
And then maybe the Department of Health
would be flexible enough to add more to
the program as we continue on.
Perfect.
Thanks for sharing that and clarifying.
Really.
Desbo,
did you have a comment to that as well?
I did,
but I actually see that Senator Steinborn
has his hand raised and I don't know if
maybe he might be answering a question
that I'm asking as well or commenting on.
Sounds good.
And we'll go to Senator Steinborn.
And Chef.
Your mic is enabled.
You can unmute when ready.
All right, thank you guys and, and,
and thank you for the opportunity to
speak.
First of all, great job everybody.
You just bring a big smile to my face
hearing all the amazing work you're doing.
So first of all,
kudos to you guys and thank you.
Secondly, I, I just, you know,
Paul raised it about the funding for the
equity fund.
So I wanted to mention a couple things
just so everyone, you know,
including Paul,
this was one time money gotten through
the legislature and there's there's no
guarantee, you know,
when it comes to future appropriations in
New Mexico, unlike the federal government,
we have a balanced budget.
It's, you know,
it's always a juggle between, you know,
what obviously what pressing things are
out there in the state and how much extra
capacity we have to do things like this,
which is amazing that we have this kind
of capacity.
A lot of states probably don't right now.
What that looks like in the future,
who knows?
So I I say that for a couple things.
I mean,
we need to really stretch the dollars as
much as possible.
And with the equity fund and maybe,
you know,
there's organizations out there maybe
cost shares and things like that.
You know,
if there's other entities sponsoring
someone's treatment or yeah,
just throw that out there,
there might be creative things that we're
considering as a program to just try to
stretch the dollars as much as possible.
But and you know, but again, there's no,
the door isn't closed on future funds
either.
That's that's definitely true.
So I think it's we're going to see how it
goes and, you know, just,
it'll be an evolving thing.
The third thing I wanted to mention was
the federal executive order.
You know,
President Trump's executive order on
psychedelics,
if you saw that a few weeks ago included
a little $50 million item for states,
$50 million that he authorized of
existing funds out there to go to states
specifically that have programs.
The language on the executive order is
pretty simple.
It seems to imply states that have
programs,
but now we have a lot of states creating
new research initiatives by the day.
Kind of I got a text from an advocate
today,
national wanting to kind of talk about
that.
So,
so I think a lot of people are looking at
that money.
I certainly am.
I sent an e-mail to one of our senators
staff in Washington drawing their
attention to the executive order included
the Department of Health and some others
on that.
So just so you know,
that $50 million is money that's
definitely on our radar.
And if we can try to bring some of that
home to help support any facet of our
program research Department of
HealthEquity fund, you know, it's just,
but right now,
I don't know there's even any ground
rules by DoH or sorry,
HHS federally for this money,
there probably isn't.
But any rate we're, we're,
I think everyone's clamoring for it.
So there's going to be a demand to help
be equitable in and of themselves for
that funds.
And I just want to mention one other
little thing that I've been thinking
about since the very beginning,
which is kind of also regarding the last
comment about safety information.
There's so many cool things out there on
like the Zendo project,
but others that are just trying to
provide harm reduction safety information
that I think it would be kind of cool and
appropriate to maybe at some point.
I know you have your hands full to create
a little safety education thing out there
where we can maybe list some of these
resource links since we are one of the
few programs out there people will be
clamoring for that kind of information.
And I think we can be a clearing house
for a lot of cool different projects out
there, including, you know,
people operating outside the program,
which we wouldn't encourage.
But nonetheless, there you go.
I'll just leave it at that.
I'm over my time.
Thank you all so much for your good work.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Senator Steinborn, sorry,
just jumped the gun.
I actually had a question to just clarify
if a Senator says find,
I know that we were saying that the funds
were non reverting.
But then there was also another thing
that we're trying to clarify.
I think as far as how far they were
extending into the fiscal year,
because I know they started in July or
they're starting this July and then they
will be available until they are until
they are maxed out or depleted and that
they are non reverting.
But I think that there was a question as
to their availability beyond the fiscal
year.
I think was maybe possibly the question.
But on that note,
it sounds like what I'm hearing too,
is that, you know,
it's really important as a community and
for anyone else who's in here is just,
you know,
making sure that the the our
representatives know how important that
this is.
You know,
when it comes time for this next
legislature in January,
it's going to be a long one.
It's going to be 60 days.
But this is really the time to, you know,
find out who are actually, you know,
working,
creating more legislation bills and
etcetera, asking for these funds to be,
you know, replenished and or allocated,
making sure that there's also the healing
advocacy fund.
We're going to be hearing from,
I believe Hanifa and Denali on Tuesday.
So it's really important to realize that,
you know, if you have an idea, you know,
find your common people in alignment with
the people who are who,
who are wanting to advocate for this.
And it can be very specific and much to
senators, you know, call to action for us,
you know, how are we going to, you know,
the $50 million money will be there
dangling in front of us till the end of
time.
But the problem I've seen so far is like
the specifics and how to allocate that
money.
There has to be a framework and a
scaffolding of exactly how that's going
to be executed.
And that's what will get people to listen
to you.
That's what will get conversations going.
And so really being, you know, like, hey,
this is exactly how we're going to be
able to use money.
This is exactly who we're going to be
targeting for.
You know,
these types of things will actually,
you know,
that's the thing that people want to hear
whenever they're being asked to give
money or spend money or use money.
And that's also the disappointment when
we find out.
Well, they had, you know, $1,000,
000 for this.
Like what happened to it?
It's because the,
the planning needs to be there.
So even if we don't have the money
available,
what is the dream that you need to be
able to have for this thing?
Right?
Put the planning in action.
I think that the senator might want to
respond, though.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
And then and then I just wanted to put
one more thing and then I'll give the mic
back to senator.
It was just the EMS response.
I'm not.
I mean,
that would be great to be able to have
recommendations for us or anybody else.
But I, I, as far as I understand,
you know,
we want people to be there to support
others.
And sometimes even if we ask,
they may not be willing.
I feel like, you know.
Yeah.
So, you know,
that's something to be thinking about.
We we can put recommendations and we can
ask people to be there for others.
And sometimes it may not, It may,
it may fall on deaf ears.
So that's it.
And then, Senator,
I don't know if you needed to respond
back to some of those with the Tesla.
And then we can go to Jason and yeah,
just real briefly, I, I,
I totally agree Desbaugh on the
scaffolding and it's cool the work you're
doing like thinking through all the
different ways that someone would need to
be supported to use the program.
And I think that's great.
And it's be really interesting to see
what you guys come up with.
Yes, the fund is non reverting.
So the money is there until we use it.
So you don't have to worry about it,
about us losing it.
It's not going to go away.
And you know,
the session is going to be right after
the program starts,
so I can't imagine we'll go through it
all in one month or two months,
but any rate.
But yeah, there you have it.
As far as raising more money from the
Legislature, though,
I want to kind of just flag,
I think something more urgent but not
necessarily less important,
but but which is that for the Department
of Health itself?
We got seed funding for the program,
which was $1,000,000.
We had initially asked for two.
I think I'm speaking for myself here,
not for the department unless when,
you know,
until they're ready to kind of have this
conversation and they do this internally
before anything goes public.
But I think there's a need for more
funding for the program itself just to
hire some additional staff.
This has been a great roll out.
But as a legislator and just in,
in terms of our legislative advocacy,
let's all be aware that kind of like what
is the matrix of things we're going to be
out raising money for?
And the Department of Health will be kind
of at the top of the list for the program
itself.
So,
but then certainly more money for equity
and research and things like that are are
always going to be welcome.
So just want to flag that for you guys as
we think about the next session.
Like we launched this program,
but now we have a new administration
coming in.
So the these kinds of programs when they
get started get built into base budgets
of departments.
But at what base budget level will it be
recommended from this administration to
the next?
It needs to be at a higher level in which
we launched it.
And so this is kind of internal advocacy
for this administration,
but also the next just to make sure the
program is fully,
fully funded on a staffing level,
but then these other things as well.
All right, that's all I have.
Thanks, guys.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Appreciate that.
All right, and let's see,
we are going to go to Jason Burge.
And Jason, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
All right, Thank you.
Yes, My name's Jason Burge,
and I'm with the Suicide Assisted Therapy
Association and one of our programs is
First Responder Collective.
I'm a retired first responder.
Please use the state programs to address
PTSD.
I really want to just kind of piggyback
on what Paul was saying on the importance
of educating all of the first responders
that are out there.
Because as we've seen in Oregon and in
Colorado,
which we've been involved in in both of
those states as well, is that you get it,
an increase of unregulated use
psychedelics in the states when these
programs come in because attention is
being drawn to them.
So educating the the first responders on
how to respond is more than just
educating on how to respond to a,
you know, a regulated program, Paul.
It's also responding to all of, you know,
any other potential emergencies that are
out there.
And we're developing training around that.
And if there's any way that we can help
or participate with that,
we would love to.
And I really believe that these programs
should be delivered by first responders
to the first responder departments
themselves,
because first responders educating each
other is very different than somebody
else who hasn't actually been in those
emergency situations.
This really all comes down to that,
you know, that safety being the central,
central piece.
I would like to say thank you all for
what you're doing and any way that we can
help participate, you know,
to make the program a success.
We're we're there.
Appreciate it Jason, Thank you.
And then on that,
I wanted to read in from the chat into
the record, Robert Truchter.
Paul,
this is Robert Truchter and I've been
thinking about your question of
preparation EMS for field response.
I think education is a great idea.
Doctor Lehman posted a flyer for group
psilocybin therapy for veterans and 1st
responders with PTSD.
We are now open for people who are
interested to apply.
This is with whole psilocybin mushrooms
in alignment with our state program.
Feel free to share the flyer which has QR
link.
Thank you.
Senator Paul Walton.
Thank you.
Senator Robert Ruckner,
I'd love to help with that back from Paul.
And then Chris discussed with two Gregory
Evans.
Yes, thank you.
And that's my good note, Senator.
It's good to know what specifics needed
to be focused on as we move along.
Eileen Brewer,
we started a list of third party
resources, for example,
Zendo Fireside for the public as part of
the research and continuous Improvement
Committee.
Happy to share with anyone who wants to
add it.
And I think we're ready for James Brown.
All right.
And James, your mic is enabled.
You can unmute.
Morning, everyone.
And again, you know,
thank you so much to the board members
and to the DoH for, you know,
for having this the where we can come and
present ourselves and talk to you guys
and let you know our comments.
But also just for your time, you know,
this space is very important and that
these people's containers are very
important that we fulfill what we need to
change and what we need to do in this
great momentum time that we're in right
now.
I think New Mexico is in a great place to
be forefront and to be leading this
industry.
We need to look at that and and think
about that with our filters that we use.
And one of those and I that's the theme
that we're hearing.
It's something that I wanted to bring up
earlier was some type of quality review
board.
I believe that the DoH needs a process
for a quality review board that will help
to reduce this,
what we call harm reduction in this space.
Colorado and Oregon have a great setup.
They have some great tools.
They have some great things that we can
use.
But again, this is New Mexico.
We have, we're more rural than they are.
We have to think about that.
We have to think about our economy.
It's a lot different than both of those
states.
And so with those filters that we're
thinking of,
we really need to think about that harm
reduction process and what can we get
from the data that we're going to be
collecting.
I think that's going to be the key.
I've always been a big believer of what
do you do with the data that you collect?
If you don't do anything with it,
don't collect it.
So what are we going to do with it?
DoH in New Mexico?
That's going to be a big important thing
that we need to discuss.
And with that data,
harm reduction is going to be in there.
And so as we keep hearing whether it's a
challenging event that we like to use
right in the moment and and that person
trying to adjust their container could
have challenging events,
but it or is that a more adverse event
and something that really needs to be
addressed by EMS that needs to be
escalated.
And that's in the training, right,
that we're going to adjust,
but that needs to be adjusted with a
thought process of some type of quality
review process of the DoH coming up with
members of its own, maybe board members,
but also independent professionals who
are out there in the communities that
they would like to see on this quality
review board that would be reviewing
these challenging events,
but also adverse events that come up so
that we can use this harm reduction data
in a constructive way also that can be
used for money.
If you guys think about the data that's
created, that also leads to funding.
And so I just wanted to let you guys know
that that's a big piece I'd like to see,
but I'd also like to see that with the
individual, either facilitators,
individual practitioners.
Again, definitions is a huge thing here.
You know,
we need to nail down these definitions.
Like we've been saying,
once these definitions are laid down,
I think it'll be very important
foundations.
But this thing needs to be laid down with
individuals.
I think harm reduction should start with
the individual facilitator.
Again, the practitioner, the center,
all those need to have a harm reduction
process and procedure.
That's not a guideline.
Again, it's not a guideline.
This is a process and a procedure.
That's a policy.
This needs to be laid out to be very,
very clear that that these policies are
there and that we're going to be
collecting this type of data in positive
ways and,
and also negative outcomes as well,
which I'm hoping are very minimal.
But we need to think about that on those
levels that each center will have a harm
reduction process.
And so when you guys go in to inspect
them,
you'll have those harm reduction
processes, you know, reviewed.
And so that's just my idea there,
as you know,
as I think that would be some teeth in to
help with harm reduction.
Thank you again so much for what the
board's doing.
I really appreciate you guys and thank
you make you change.
Appreciate it and make sure that, I mean,
I know you're on the intercessional work
group for the Racy committee because
that's exactly where we want y'all to
make those recommendations to say this is
the exact framework that we would like to
see.
And if you want some specifics in there,
you're in the right spot for that.
So thanks for your participation in that
and for the passion for that too.
That's exactly who we need.
So thank you adding into from Eileen
Brewer's comment,
Leap maps and a few others have programs
to educate law enforcement first
responders might be worth reaching out to
them.
And as we approach the end of our time
here,
if you want to send any kind of written
public comment and make sure you send it
to themedical.sosimon@doh.nm.
gov address and you can include in the
comment line for this one the board as a
subject line.
If you're referring to any specific
documents,
then make make sure that you do not
include the document,
but just give us a hyperlink to it.
If you do send documents,
provide the snippet and the context and
their comments are related to the topics
discussed in the minutes and other
details there.
No more than 3 pages and include your
full legal name and organizational
affiliations by 5:00 PM of this business
day after the meeting.
And I see no other hands up and we are
about 6 minutes to the end.
So I wanted to thank everybody very much
for being here today for the board
meeting and I appreciate y'all's ability
to let me lead you through this as Co
chair.
Thank you again very much.
Our next board meeting will be June 26th
from 9:00 to 11:00.
And don't forget we have plenty of other
committees that have their next meetings
coming up.
So please,
DAZ boss meeting is coming up May 19th,
training and education is coming up on
the 22nd,
qualification and safety on the 26th,
doses on the 27th and end of life on the
5th.
And then on June 12th,
the racy committee and that will be on
the reporting framework.
Appreciate everybody being here and have
a great rest of your week weekend and
we'll see you back next month.
Thank you, Dan,
for stepping in and thank you to
everybody for being here today.
Hope you all have a great weekend and
thank you very much on behalf of the
department.